<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<ModMetaData>
    <packageId>jellypowered.survivaltools.testing</packageId>
    <name>Survival Tools Reborn (testing branch)</name>
    <author>Jellypowered</author>
    <url>https://github.com/Jellypowered/SurvivalTools/tree/Refactor/1.6</url>
    <supportedVersions>
        <li>1.6</li>
    </supportedVersions>
    <description><![CDATA[
Current version: v2.1 (February 2026)

Transforms RimWorld into a challenging tool-dependent survival experience where proper equipment becomes essential for colony success.

⚠️ REFACTOR BRANCH - TESTING BUILD ⚠️
This is a complete rewrite with major improvements but may contain bugs. Please report issues you encounter.

KEY FEATURES:
• Smart Tool Assignment: Automated system finds and equips optimal tools before work begins
• Right-Click Rescue: Prioritize actions by acquiring needed tools with a single click
• Hardcore Mode: Tools become essential - most work impossible without proper equipment
• Nightmare Mode: Ultimate challenge with carry limit 1 and strict tool requirements
• Granular Controls: Choose exactly which tasks require tools (cleaning, butchery, medical)
• Anti-Thrashing Logic: Prevents excessive tool swapping for minor stat gains
• Realistic Degradation: Tools wear down with use and must be maintained or replaced
• Early Game Survival: Find tools in ruins or craft them to establish your colony

DIFFICULTY MODES:
• Normal: Tools improve efficiency but work remains possible without them
• Hardcore: Most tasks require proper tools, penalties for working without them
• Nightmare: Strict carry limits and mandatory tool requirements

WHAT'S NEW IN REFACTOR:
• Complete architecture rewrite with deterministic tool decisions
• Fixed crashes and infinite tool-swap loops from earlier versions
• 97% reduction in log spam through intelligent throttling
• Research jobs now respect critical needs (food, rest, mood)
• Alert system only shows for work actually assigned to pawns
• Better mod compatibility with automatic tool detection
• Significant performance improvements with optimized hot paths
• Virtual tool support (cloth/wool for cleaning, medical work)

COMPATIBILITY:
• Works with Separate Tree Chopping, Combat Extended, and other major mods
• Automatic tool detection for modded items
• Tree chopping integration with multiple tree-related mods

Originally by XeoNovaDan. Completely rebuilt for RimWorld 1.6 with modern architecture, intelligent automation, and focus on stability. This test branch represents a systematic ground-up refactor.

Report bugs with your log file and reproduction steps!
    ]]>    </description>
</ModMetaData>